A Guide to the Kent's Store Records, 1868-1947
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Kent's Store Records 1868-1947
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms89-004
125 containers; 57 cu. ft.
Business records of Kent's Store in Fluvanna County, Virginia. Account books, including daybooks, journals and ledgers maintained by general mercantile businesses Kent & Parrish, G. H. Kent & Co. and G. H. Kent. Other records include cash books; bill books; post office ledgers; pharmaceutical, fertilizer, mill work, and blacksmith account ledgers; and James M. Kent estate records.
Creator
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Kent's Store Records were purchased by Special Collections in 1989.
Biographical Information
James Madison Kent, son of John and Elizabeth Baskett Kent, was born in Virginia in 1819. In 1845, Kent purchased from Longston Mosby a tract of land in Fluvanna County, Virginia and built a residence and store near what is today the intersection of Route 601 and Kents Store Way. By 1868, Kent had partnered with his future brother-in-law, Booker Parrish, to form Kent & Parrish, and in 1870, he married Elizabeth Parrish. The couple would have two sons, George Henry and James Aubrey Kent.
Kent & Parrish grew quickly, and by 1870, it had become one of the largest general mercantile stores in Virginia, selling primarily household goods but also catering to the wagon traffic that stopped there en route to deliver tobacco and other products to the James River Canal at Columbia.
George Henry Kent, oldest son of James and Elizabeth Parrish Kent, was born in Fluvanna County on March 6, 1853. He established the Kent's Store post office in 1874, thus giving the community an official name. Upon the death of his father (August 25, 1883), Kent continued to serve as postmaster while he and his younger brother James assumed operation of the store under the name G. H. Kent & Company. George H. Kent married Florence Mary Wood in 1881, and the couple had seven children.
Records within the collection indicate that under Kent's management, the store expanded into pharmaceutical and fertilizer sales and began the wholesale buying and selling of locally produced goods (farm crops, livestock, animal skins, etc.).
G. H. Kent & Company seems to have passed into trusteeship under S. M. Shepherd in 1903, with the remaining store inventory sold to H. R. Adams. The records within the collection indicate that George Kent purchased the store's pharmaceutical inventory and continued to operate a shop there, doing business under his own name. Following Kent's death (November 16, 1936), the business apparently continued to be operated by family members as late as 1947.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of financial records maintained by Kent & Parrish, G. H. Kent & Company, and G. H. Kent, successive owners of a general mercantile store at Kent's Store (Fluvanna County), Virginia. The majority of the collection is comprised of daybooks, journals and their corresponding account ledgers, but it also includes other types of business records such as bill books, cash books, and petty ledgers, relating not only to the store's operation but to several related enterprises, including a post office, pharmaceutical sales, fertilizer purchases and sales, a blacksmith's shop, and a livery stable. The collection also contains records relating to the administration of James M. Kent's estate.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by item type, then chronologically, within the following series:
SERIES I: DAYBOOKS, 1869-1903. This series contains daybooks maintained by Kent & Parrish and G. H. Kent & Company. Recorded within the day books are all of the transactions at the store for each day of operation. Each entry provides the customer's name, items purchased, and amounts owed or paid. Entries for credit transactions were marked with a check and copied to the corresponding journal for that date. The final book for Kent & Parrish commences in 1883, the year of James M. Kent's death, and runs through 1901, with later entries detailing the settlement of existing accounts. Daybooks for G. H. Kent & Company commence immediately upon assumption of the store's operation in August 1883 and continue through 1903, when the company went into trusteeship and the use of daybooks was discontinued. The series is arranged chronologically.
SERIES II: JOURNALS, 1868-1947. This series contains business journals maintained by Kent & Parrish, G. H. Kent & Company, and G. H. Kent. Like the daybooks, the journals contain records of the store's daily transactions. While the daybooks recorded every transaction, however, only credit transactions were copied to the early journals. The journals sometimes record the details of the transaction but often only summaries, including customer name and amounts owed or paid. Accompanying each entry is the page number on which the customer's account may be found in the corresponding account ledger. The final journal for Kent & Parrish concludes in 1899, as accounts continued to be settled long after James M. Kent's 1883 death. The G. H. Kent & Company journals commence in 1883, running through 1903, when the store was placed under the trusteeship of S. M. Shepherd. The trusteeship journals span the years 1903 to 1910. Journals from 1906 to 1947 were maintained by G. H. Kent, conducting business under his own name, and by his heirs after his death in 1936. Beginning in 1906, the journals also include the store's cash transactions. The series is arranged chronologically.
SERIES III: ACCOUNT LEDGERS, 1868-1926. This series contains store ledgers maintained by Kent & Parrish, G. H. Kent & Company, and G. H. Kent. The credit transactions recorded within the daily journals are reconciled here in the account ledgers. The accounts of each credit customer are detailed, including names, dates of purchases, and amounts owed and paid. The accounts are not arranged in any logical order within the ledgers, but each volume includes an alphabetical index, arranged by customer name. A single customer's account may span several pages within an individual ledger and may continue for many years through several volumes. The account ledgers for Kent & Parrish continue through 1895, as accounts continued to be settled long after ownership had passed to G. H. Kent & Company. Likewise, two G. H. Kent & Company ledgers commenced in 1903 continue long past the company's dissolution and were used for the final settlement of existing accounts. Finally, the G. H. Kent ledgers, which commence with Kent's purchase of the store's pharmaceutical inventory in 1906, continue through 1926. The series is arranged chronologically.
SERIES IV: OTHER BUSINESS AND FINANCIAL RECORDS, 1874-1934. This series contains other business and personal financial records of the Kent family. Most of these records relate to the operation of Kent & Parrish and G. H. Kent & Company, as well as a few records relating to the administration of James M. Kent's estate, and other financial / legal matters.
Included in the series are such materials as bill ledgers, cash books, and an 1886 inventory, all relating to the store's operation, as well as records tracking the transactions of a number of related businesses. Among these is a volume relating to pharmaceutical sales that lists customers for various poisons, venereal medications, and paregoric). Also included within this series are records relating to the purchasing and selling of apples and fertilizer, a livery stable, mill work, and the store's post office. The series contains a single accounts ledger for blacksmith James Parrish, who seems to have leased his shop from the Kents. The series also contains three ledgers which seem to be related to the store but remain unidentified.
Also within this series are volumes not directly relating to the store's business, including several concerning the administration of the estates of James M. Kent and Rev. Stephen Eastin. Another ledger details the accounts of the Byrd Chapel Building Committee. Completing the series are a few fragments from other related records. The series is arranged by document type, then chronologically.
OVERSIZE MATERIALS, 1871-1907. Contained here are materials too large to fit in their respective series.
Contents List
- SERIES I: DAYBOOKS 1869-1903
  - Kent & Parrish
    - Nov 17 1869 - Apr 19 1870 (Box-folder 1-1)
    - May 10 - Jul 5 1870 (Box-folder 1-2)
    - Aug 26 - Oct 25 1870 (Box-folder 1-3)
    - Oct 25 1870 - Apr 29 1871 (Box-folder 2-1-3)
    - May 1 - Nov 30 1871 (Box-folder 3-1-3)
    - Dec 1 1871 - Aug 9 1872 (Box-folder 4-1-3)
    - Aug 10 - Oct 5 1872 (Box-folder 5-1)
    - Nov 29 1872 - Feb 10 1873 (Box-folder 5-2)
    - May 14 - Aug 12 1873 (Box-folder 5-3)
    - Aug 13 1873 - Mar 20 1874 (Box-folder 6-1-3)
    - Mar 21 - Jul 15 1874 (Box-folder 7-1)
    - Dec 19 1874 - Jul 5 1875 (Box-folder 7-2-3)
    - Jul 6 - Dec 27 1875 (Box-folder 8-1-3)
    - Dec 27 1875 - Sep 26 1876 (Box-folder 9-1-3)
    - Sep 26 1876 - Jul 7 1877 (Box-folder 10-1-3)
    - Jul 7 1877 - Mar 25 1878 (Box-folder 11-1-3)
    - Mar 26 - Jan 17 1879 (Box-folder 12-1-3)
    - Jan 17 - Oct 28 1879 (Box-folder 13-1-3)
    - Oct 30 1879 - Apr 19 1880 (Box-folder 14-1-2)
    - Apr 19 - Nov 6 1880 (Box-folder 15-1-3)
    - Nov 8 1880 - Sep 3 1881 (Box-folder 16-1-3)
    - Sep 5 1881 - Jun 6 1882 (Box-folder 17-1-3)
    - Jun 6 1882 - Apr 9 1883 (Box-folder 18-1-3)
    - Apr 9 1883 - Aug 17 1901 (Box-folder 19-1-2)
  - G. H. Kent & Company
    - Aug 27 1883 - Jul 8 1884 (Box-folder 20-1-3)
    - Jul 8 - Dec 25 1884 (Box-folder 21-1-2)
    - Dec 26 1884 - Jun 8 1885 (Box-folder 22-1-2)
    - Jun 8 - Dec 17 1885 (Box-folder 23-1-3)
    - Dec 18 1885 - Aug 10 1886 (Box-folder 24-1-3)
    - Aug 11 1886 - Jun 6 1887 (Box-folder 25-1-3)
    - Aug 30 1887 - Jun 1 1888 (Box-folder 26-1-3)
    - Jun 1 - Aug 18 1888 (Box-folder 27-1)
    - Nov 16 1888 - Apr 22 1889 (Box-folder 27-2-3)
    - Apr 23 - Dec 13 1889 (Box-folder 28-1-3)
    - Dec 14 1889 - Oct 25 1890 (Box-folder 29-1-3)
    - Oct 27 1890 - Jun 2 1891 (Box-folder 30-1-2)
    - Jun 3 - Dec 5 1891 (Box-folder 31-1-2)
    - Dec 7 1891 - Jun 8 1892 (Box-folder 32-1-2)
    - Aug 29 - Nov 19 1892 (Box-folder 32-3)
    - Nov 21 1892 - Aug 29 1893 (Box-folder 33-1-3)
    - Aug 30 1893 - Jun 21 1894 (Box-folder 34-1-3)
    - Jun 22 1894 - Apr 24 1895 (Box-folder 35-1-3)
    - Apr 24 - Oct 28 1895 (Box-folder 36-1-2)
    - Oct 28 1895 - May 27 1896 (Box-folder 37-1-2)
    - May 28 1896 - Jan 23 1897 (Box-folder 38 -1-2)
    - Jan 25 - Aug 13 1897 (Box-folder 39-1-2)
    - Nov 15 1897 - Feb 18 1898 (Box-folder 39-3)
    - Feb 19 - Oct 15 1898 (Box-folder 40-1-3)
    - Oct 17 1898 - May 27 1899 (Box-folder 41-1-3)
    - May 29 1899 - Jan 13 1900 (Box-folder 42-1-3)
    - Apr 20 - Dec 24 1900 (Box-folder 43-1-2)
    - Oct 6 1900 - Jul 16 1901 (Box-folder 44-1-3)
    - Jul 17 1901 - May 12 1902 (Box-folder 45-1-3)
    - May 13 1902 - Mar 24 1903 (Box-folder 46-1-3)
    - Mar 25 - Aug 27 1903 (Box-folder 47-1)
- SERIES II: JOURNALS 1868-1947
  - Kent & Parrish
    - Apr 22 - Sep 9 1868 (Box-folder 47-2)
    - Sep 1 1869 - Feb 11 1870 (Box-folder 47-3)
    - Feb 12 - Aug 20 1870 (Box-folder 48-1)
    - Feb 24 1872 - Jul 22 1872 (Box-folder 48-2)
    - Jul 22 1872 - May 12 1873 (Box-folder 49-1-2)
    - May 12 - Dec 23 1873 (Box-folder 50-1-2)
    - Dec 23 1873 - May 18 1875 (Box-folder 51-1-2)
    - May 18 1875 - Apr 18 1876 (Box-folder 52-1-2)
    - Apr 19 1876 - Feb 1 1877 (Box-folder 53-1-2)
    - Feb 1 - Jul 27 1877 (Box 54)
    - Jul 28 - Dec 13 1877 (Box 55)
    - Dec 13 1877 - Jun 20 1878 (Box 56)
    - Jun 20 1878 - Jul 10 1879 (Box-folder 57-1-2)
    - Jul 11 1879 - Jun 19 1880 (Box-folder 58-1-2)
    - Jun 19 1880 - Jan 28 1881 (Box 59)
    - Jan 28 - Aug 17 1881 (Box 60)
    - Aug 18 1881 - Mar 20 1882 (Box 61)
    - Mar 20 1882 - May 5 1883 (Box-folder 62-1-2)
    - May 5 1883 - Nov 7 1899 (Box-folder 63-1)
  - G. H. Kent & Company
    - Aug 28 1883 - Mar 20 1884 (Box-folder 63-2)
    - Mar 20 1884 - Apr 1 1885 (Box-folder 64-1-2)
    - Apr 1 1885 - Jan 2 1886 (Box-folder 65-1-2)
    - Jan 2 - Dec 29 1886 (Box-folder 66-1-2)
    - Dec 30 1886 - Aug 6 1887 (Box 67)
    - Aug 6 1887 - Apr 12 1888 (Box 68)
    - Apr 13 - Sep 18 1888 (Box 69)
    - Sep 18 1888 - Jul 1 1889 (Box-folder 70-1-2)
    - Jul 1 1889 - Jun 27 1890 (Box-folder 71-1-2)
    - Jun 27 1890 - Mar 21 1891 (Box 72)
    - Mar 23 - Sep 19 1891 (Box 73)
    - Sep 19 1891 - Mar 22 1892 (Box 74)
    - Aug 23 1892 - Aug 14 1893 (Box-folder 75-1-2)
    - Aug 14 1893 - Sep 20 1894 (Box-folder 76-1-2)
    - Sep 20 1894 - Nov 5 1895 (Box-folder 77-1-2)
    - Nov 6 1895 - Jun 10 1896 (Box 78)
    - Jun 11 - Dec 23 1896 (Box 79)
    - Dec 23 1896 - Jun 30 1897 (Box 80)
    - Jul 1 1897 - May 24 1898 (Box-folder 81-1-2)
    - May 24 1898 - Mar 31 1899 (Box-folder 82-1-2)
    - Apr 1 1899 - Jan 4 1900 (Box-folder 83-1-2)
    - Jan 5 - Nov 23 1900 (Box-folder 84-1-2)
    - Nov 24 1900 - May 21 1901 (Box 85)
    - May 22 - Nov 7 1901 (Box 86)
    - Nov 8 1901 - May 20 1902 (Box 87)
    - May 20 - Nov 21 1902 (Box 88)
    - Nov 22 1902 - Nov 11 1905 (Box 89)
    - Aug 18 1904 - Mar 28 1910 (Box-folder 90-1-2)
      [S. M. Shepherd, trustee]
  - G. H. Kent
    - Jun 1 - Dec 31 1907 (Box-folder 90-3)
    - Aug 25 1908 - Mar 16 1911 (Box-folder 91-1-3)
    - Aug 2 1913 - Nov 22 1915 (Box-folder 92-1-3)
    - Nov 23 1915 - Jul 19 1916 (Box-folder 93-1)
    - Mar 10 1925 - Mar 25 1927 (Box-folder 93-2-3)
    - Mar 26 1927 - Jul 29 1929 (Box-folder 94-1-2)
    - Jul 30 1929 - Apr 22 1932 (Box-folder 95-1-2)
    - Apr 23 1932 - May 11 1935 (Box-folder 96-1-2)
    - May 13 1935 - Sep 18 1939 (Box-folder 97-1-2)
    - Sep 21 1939 - Jan 13 1947 (Box-folder 98-1-2)
- SERIES III: LEDGERS 1868-1926
  - Kent & Parrish
    - 1868-1869 (Box 99)
    - 1869-1870 (Box 100)
    - 1874-1876 (Box 101)
    - 1876-1877 (Box 102)
    - 1877-1878 (Box 103)
    - 1879-1880 (Box 104)
    - 1881-1882 (Box 105)
    - 1882-1895 (Box 106)
  - G. H. Kent & Company
    - 1885-1887 (Box 107)
    - 1887-1889 (Box 108)
    - 1889-1891 (Box 109)
    - 1891-1893 (Box 110)
    - 1895-1896 (Box 111)
    - 1897-1898 (Box 112)
    - 1899-1901 (Box 113)
    - 1903-1921 (Box 114)
    - 1903-1911 (Box-folder 115-1)
  - G. H. Kent
    - 1906-1913 (Box-folder 115-2)
    - 1914-1916 (Box 116)
    - 1917-1920 (Box 117)
    - 1920-1926 (Box 118)
- SERIES IV: OTHER FINANCIAL RECORDS 1870-1935
  - Bill ledgers
    - Bills receivable / bills payable 1874-1883 (Box-folder 119-1)
    - Bills receivable / bills payable - Kent & Parrish 1882-1884 (Box-folder 119-2)
    - Bills receivable 1887-1898 (Box-folder 119-3)
    - Bills receivable - G. H. Kent & Company 1898-1923 (Box-folder 119-4)
    - Bills payable - G. H. Kent & Company 1897-1903 (Box-folder 119-5)
  - Bond book 1883-1905 (Box-folder 120-1)
  - Cash books
    - G. H. Kent & Company 1885-1888 (Box-folder 120-2)
    - G. H. Kent & Company 1903-1907, [see Oversize Materials]
  - Check books
    - Bank of Richmond 1904 (Box-folder 120-3)
    - State Bank of Columbia 1904 (Box-folder 120-4)
  - Deed and court judgment abstracts 1871-1904, [see Oversize Materials]
  - Inventory - G. H. Kent & Company 1886 (Box-folder 120-5)
  - Petty ledger 1893-1900 (Box-folder 120-6)
  - Fertilizer accounts ledgers
    - Fertilizer accounts ledgers 1881-1894, 1896-1899 (Box-folder 121-2)
      [also includes wholesale accounts, 1877-1903; for 1895 fertilizer accounts, see milll book, 1892-1903]
    - 1900-1904 (Box-folder 121-3)
    - 1904-1905 (Box-folder 121-4)
      [also includes livery stable accounts, 1897-1900]
  - Mill book 1892-1903 (Box-folder 121-5)
    [also includes fertilizer accounts, 1895]
  - James Parrish blacksmith shop book 1888-1890 (Box-folder 121-6)
  - Pharmacy ledger 1918-1924 (Box-folder 121-7)
    [also includes lists of poisons, venereal medicines and paregoric dispensed to customers, 1894-1934]
  - Post office book 1891-1902 (Box-folder 121-7)
    [daily tabulations of stamps cancelled]
  - Post office money order cash books 1899-1912 (Box-folder 122-2-4)
  - Unidentified accounts ledgers
    - 1885-1899 (Box-folder 122-5)
    - 1924-1935 (Box-folder 123-1-2)
  - James M. Kent estate
    - Accounts 1883-1889 (Box-folder 123-3)
    - Appraiser's book 1883 (Box-folder 123-4)
    - Day book 1883-1889 (Box-folder 123-5)
    - Letter book 1888-1889 (Box-folder 124-1)
  - Rev. Stephen Eastin estate 1870-1872 (Box-folder 124-2)
  - Byrd Chapel Building Committee ledger 1906-1910 (Box-folder 124-3)
  - Record fragments 1878-1895 (Box-folder 124-4)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS 1871-1907
  - Cash book - G. H. Kent & Company 1903-1907 (Box-folder 125-1)
  - Deed and court judgment abstracts 1871-1904 (Box-folder 125-2)